By now you've seen the anomaly
在此之前 你已经学习了
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
detection algorithm and we've
异常检测算法 并且
also talked about how to
我们也讨论了如何
evaluate an anomaly detection
评估一个异常检测算法
algorithm. It turns out,
事实上
that when you're applying anomaly
当你应用异常检测时
detection, one of the
对它的效率
things that has a huge
影响最大的
effect on how well it
因素之一是
does, is what features you
你使用什么特征变量
use, and what features you choose,
你选择什么特征变量
to give the anomaly detection algorithm.
来输入异常检测算法
So in this video, what I'd
那么 在本视频中
like to do is say a few
我将要做的事情就是
words, give some suggestions and
给你们一些建议
guidelines for how to
关于如何设计或选择
go about designing or selecting
异常检测算法的
features give to an anomaly detection algorithm.
特征变量
In our anomaly detection algorithm,
在我们的异常检测算法中
one of the things we did was
我们做的事情之一就是
model the features using this sort of Gaussian distribution.
使用这种正态(高斯)分布来对特征向量建模
With xi to mu
就是有 xi 服从正态分布 期望为μi
i, sigma squared i, lets say.
方差为 σi 平方
And so one thing that
那么 我常做的一件事
I often do would be to plot the
就是画出这些数据
data or the histogram of
或者用直方图表示数据
the data, to make sure that
以确保
the data looks vaguely
这些数据在
Gaussian before feeding it
应用我的异常检测算法前
to my anomaly detection algorithm.
看起来像高斯分布
And, it'll usually work okay,
当然即使你的数据并不是高斯分布
even if your data isn't Gaussian,
它也基本上可以良好地运行
but this is sort of a nice sanitary check to run.
And by the way, in case your data
如果你的数据
looks non-Gaussian, the algorithms will often work just find.
看起来不像正态分布 算法也常常可以正常运行
But, concretely if I
但是具体而言
plot the data like this,
我将数据画成这样
and if it looks like a histogram like
如果它的柱状图看起来
this, and the way
像这样 另外说一下
to plot a histogram is to
画柱状图的方法是
use the HIST, or the
使用 hist 命令
HIST command in Octave,
就是 Octave 里面的 hist 命令
but it looks like this, this looks
但看起来好像
vaguely Gaussian, so if
这个图形近似像一个高斯分布
my features look like this,
所以如果我的特征变量是这样的
I would be pretty happy feeding into my algorithm.
那么我可以很高兴地把它们送入我的学习算法了
But if i were to plot a histogram of my
但如果我画出来的
data, and it were
直方图是这样的话
to look like this well, this
好吧
doesn't look at all like a
那么这就看起来完全不像钟形曲线
bell shaped curve, this is a very asymmetric distribution,
这个分布很不对称
it has a peak way off to one side.
它的峰值非常偏向一边
If this is what my data
如果我的数据是这样的话
looks like, what I'll often
通常我要做的事情
do is play with different
是对数据进行一些不同的转换
transformations of the data in order
来确保这些数据
to make it look more Gaussian.
看起来更像高斯分布
And again the algorithm will usually work okay, even if you don't.
虽然通常来说你不这么做 算法也会运行地很好
But if you use these transformations
但如果你使用一些转换方法
to make your data more gaussian, it might work a bit better.
使你的数据更像高斯分布的话 你的算法会工作得更好
So given the data set
所以
that looks like this, what I
如果给我这样的数据集
might do is take a
我通常要做的是
log transformation of the
进行一个求对数的转换
data and if i
如果我这样做的话
do that and re-plot the
重新把直方图画出来
histogram, what I end up
对于这个具体的例子
with in this particular example,
我就会得到
is a histogram that looks like this.
像这样的一个直方图
And this looks much more Gaussian, right?
这样就看起来更像高斯分布了 对吧？
This looks much more like the classic
这看起来就更像
bell shaped curve, that we
典型的钟形曲线
can fit with some mean and variance paramater sigma.
这样我就能拟合出期望和方差参数了
So what I mean by taking
所以这里我说的
a log transform, is really that
进行一个取对数的转换
if I have some feature x1 and
意思是这样的
then the histogram of x1 looks
如果我有一个特征变量 比如 x1
like this then I might
直方图是这样的
take my feature x1
那么我就用 x1 的对数
and replace it with log
log(x1) 来替换掉 x1
of x1 and this is
所以 经过替换
my new x1 that I'll plot
这就是我的新 x1
to the histogram over on the right, and this looks much
我把它的直方图画在右边
more Guassian.
这看起来更像高斯分布了
Rather than just a log transform some other things you can
除了取对数变换之外
do, might be, let's say
还有别的一些方法也可以用
I have a different feature x2,
假如这是另一个特征 x2
maybe I'll replace that will
现在我用 log(x2 + 1) 来取代
log x plus 1,
或者更一般地
or more generally with log
我可以在 x2 后面加上
x with x2 and
某个常数 c
some constant c and this
然后求对数来取代 x2
constant could be something
我会调整这个常数 c 的值
that I play with, to try to make it look as Gaussian as possible.
使得这个分布看起来尽可能地像高斯分布
Or for a different feature x3, maybe
或者对于另一个特征 x3
I'll replace it with x3,
也许我可以用
I might take the square root.
它的平方根来取代
The square root is just x3 to the power of one half, right?
x3 的平方根也就是 x3 的二分之一次方 对吧？
And this one half
而这个 二分之一
is another example of a parameter I can play with.
又是一个可以由我来确定的参数
So, I might have x4 and
所以 或许对另一个特征 x4
maybe I might instead replace
我可以用 x4 的另一个幂次方
that with x4 to the power
来取代 x4
of something else, maybe to the
比如说可以用
power of 1/3.
三分之一次幂
And these, all of
所有这些
these, this one, this
所有这些参数
exponent parameter, or the
这个指数参数
C parameter, all of these
或者这个参数 c
are examples of parameters that
所有这些参数你都可以进行调整
you can play with in order
目的只有一个
to make your data look a little bit more Gaussian.
就是让数据看起来更像高斯分布
So, let me show you a live demo
下面我给你演示一下
of how I actually go about
如何对这些参数进行调整
playing with my data to make it look more Gaussian.
来让我的数据看起来更像高斯分布
So, I have already loaded
这里我已经在 Octave 中
in to octave here a set
加载了一系列特征 x
of features x I have a thousand examples
这里我加载了1000个样本
loaded over there.
So let's pull up the histogram of my data.
所以让我们来画出数据的直方图
Use the hist x command.
使用 hist(x) 命令
So there's my histogram.
这就是我的直方图了
By default, I think this
默认情况下
uses 10 bins of histograms,
直方图有十个柱
but I want to see a more fine grid histogram.
可以重新把样条设置地更好一点
So we do hist to the x, 50,
我们输入 hist(x, 50)
so, this plots it in 50 different bins.
这样就画出了50个柱
Okay, that looks better.
这样看起来好多了
Now, this doesn't look very Gaussian, does it?
但现在看起来还不够"高斯"
So, lets start playing around with the data.
所以下面我们来调整一下参数
Lets try a hist of
首先试试 x 的0.5次方
x to the 0.5.
也就是说
So we take the
我们对数据取平方根
square root of the data, and plot that histogram.
然后画出直方图
And, okay, it looks
好了 现在看起来
a little bit more Gaussian, but not
有那么一点像高斯分布了
quite there, so let's play at the 0.5 parameter.
但还是不够好 我们再调整一下
Let's see.
让我们看一看
Set this to 0.2.
把0.5减小到0.2试试
Looks a little bit more Gaussian.
又更像高斯分布了一点
Let's reduce a little bit more 0.1.
我们再减小一点 试试0.1
Yeah, that looks pretty good.
耶！好极了
I could actually just use 0.1.
所以我可以使用0.1
Well, let's reduce it to 0.05.
我们再试试更小的 0.05
And, you know?
然后 你看
Okay, this looks pretty Gaussian,
这样看起来更像高斯分布了
so I can define a new
因此 我们可以定义一个
feature which is x mu equals
新的特征变量 xNew
x to the 0.05,
等于 x 的0.05次方
and now my new
现在我的新特征变量
feature x Mu looks more
xNew 比原来的特征变量
Gaussian than my previous one
看起来更具像高斯分布
and then I might instead use
因此我就可以用这个新的
this new feature to feed
特征变量来输入到我的
into my anomaly detection algorithm.
异常检测算法中
And of course, there is more than one way to do this.
当然 实现这一功能的方法不唯一
You could also have hist of log of
你也可以用 hist(log(x), 50)
x, that's another example of a transformation you can use.
这是另一种你可以选择的转换方法
And, you know, that also look pretty Gaussian.
这同样会让你的数据看起来更像高斯分布
So, I can also define x
所以 我们也可以
mu equals log of x.
让 xNew 等于 log(x)
and that would be another
这是另一种可以选用的
pretty good choice of a feature to use.
很好的特征变量
So to summarize, if you
我们来总结一下
plot a histogram with the data,
如果你画出数据的直方图
and find that it looks pretty
并且发现图形看起来
non-Gaussian, it's worth playing
非常不像正态分布
around a little bit with
那么应该进行一些
different transformations like these, to
不同的转换 就像这些
see if you can make
通过这些方法
your data look a little bit more
来让你的数据看起来
Gaussian, before you feed it to
更具有高斯分布的特点
your learning algorithm, although even if
然后你再把数据输入到学习算法
you don't, it might work okay.
虽然说 你不这么做也可以
But I usually do take this step.
但我通常还是会进行这一步
Now, the second thing I want
下面我想讲第二个问题
to talk about is, how do
那就是你如何得到
you come up with features for an anomaly detection algorithm.
异常检测算法的特征变量
And the way I often do
我通常用的办法是
so, is via an error analysis procedure.
通过一个误差分析步骤
So what I mean by that,
我的意思是
is that this is really similar
这跟我们之前
to the error analysis procedure that
学习监督学习算法时的
we have for supervised learning, where
误差分析步骤是类似的
we would train a
也就是说 我们先完整地训练出
complete algorithm, and run the
一个学习算法
algorithm on a cross validation set,
然后在一组交叉验证集上运行算法
and look at the examples it gets
然后找出那些预测出错的样本
wrong, and see if
然后再看看
we can come up with extra features
我们能否找到一些其他的特征变量
to help the algorithm do
来帮助学习算法
better on the examples
让它在那些交叉验证时
that it got wrong in the cross-validation set.
判断出错的样本中表现更好
So lets try
让我们来用一个例子
to reason through an example of this process.
详细解释一下刚才说的这一过程
In anomaly detection, we are
在异常检测中
hoping that p of x will
我们希望 p(x) 的值
be large for the normal examples
对正常样本来说是比较大的
and it will be small for the anomalous examples.
而对异常样本来说 值是很小的
And so a pretty common problem
因此 一个很常见的问题是
would be if p of x is comparable,
p(x) 是具有可比性的
maybe both are large for both the normal and the anomalous examples.
也许正常样本和异常样本的值都很大
Lets look at a specific example of that.
我们来看一个具体点的例子
Let's say that this is my unlabeled data.
假如说这是我的无标签数据
So, here I have just one
那么 我只有一个特征变量 x1
feature, x1 and so I'm gonna fit a Gaussian to this.
我要用一个高斯分布来拟合它
And maybe my Gaussian that I fit to my data looks like that.
假如我的数据拟合出的高斯分布是这样的
And now let's say I have an anomalous example,
现在假如我有一个异常样本
and let's say that my anomalous example
假如我的异常样本中
takes on an x value of 2.5.
x 的取值为2.5
So I plot my anomalous example there.
因此 我画出我的异常样本
And you know, it's kind of buried
你不难发现
in the middle of a bunch
它看起来就像被淹没在
of normal examples, and so,
一堆正常样本中似的
just this anomalous example
我用绿色画出来的
that I've drawn in green, it gets a
这个异常样本
pretty high probability, where it's the
它的概率值很大
height of the blue curve,
是蓝色曲线的高度
and the algorithm fails to
而我们的算法
flag this as an anomalous example.
没能把这个样本判断为异常
Now, if this were maybe aircraft
现在如果说这代表
engine manufacturing or something, what
飞机引擎的制造或者别的什么
I would do is, I would actually
那么我会做的是
look at my training examples and
我会看看我的训练样本
look at what went wrong with
然后看看到底是
that particular aircraft engine, and
哪一个具体的飞机引擎出错了
see, if looking at that
看看通过这个样本
example can inspire me to
能不能启发我
come up with a new feature
想出一个新的特征 x2
x2, that helps to distinguish
来帮助算法区别出
between this bad example, compared
不好的样本
to the rest of my
和我剩下的正确的样本
red examples, compared to all
也就是那些红色的叉叉
of my normal aircraft engines.
或者说正常的飞机引擎样本
And if I managed to do
如果我这样做的话
so, the hope would be then,
我们的期望是
that, if I can create a
创建一个新的特征
new feature, X2, so that
x2 使得
when I re-plot my data, if
当我重新画数据时
I take all my normal examples
如果我用训练集中的
of my training set, hopefully
所有正常样本
I find that all my training
我应该就会发现
examples are these red crosses here.
所有的训练样本都是这里的红叉了
And hopefully, if I find
我们也希望能看到
that for my anomalous example, the
对于异常样本
feature x2 takes on the the unusual value.
这个新特征变量 x2 的值会看起来是异常的
So for my green example
因此对于我这里的绿色的样本
here, this anomaly, right, my
这是异常的样本 对吧
X1 value, is still 2.5.
我的 x1 值仍然是2.5
Then maybe my X2 value, hopefully
那么我的 x2 很有可能
it takes on a very large
是一个比较大的值
value like 3.5 over there,
比如这里的3.5
or a very small value.
或者一个非常小的值
But now, if I model
现在如果我再来给数据建模
my data, I'll find that
我会发现
my anomaly detection algorithm gives
我的异常检测算法
high probability to data
会在中间区域
in the central regions, slightly lower
给出一个较高的概率
probability to that, sightly lower probability to that.
然后越到外层越小
An example that's all the
到了那个绿色的样本
way out there, my algorithm will
我的异常检测算法
now give very low probability
会给出非常小的概率值
to.
And so, the process of this
所以这个过程
is, really look at the
实际上就是
mistakes that it is making.
看看哪里出了错
Look at the anomaly that the algorithm
看看那些
is failing to flag, and see
算法没能正确标记的异常点
if that inspires you to create some new feature.
看看你能不能得到启发来创造新的特征变量
So find something unusual about
所以也就是说
that aircraft engine and use
找一找飞机引擎中的不寻常的问题
that to create a new feature,
然后来建立一些新特征变量
so that with this new
有了这些新的特征变量
feature it becomes easier to
应该就能更容易
distinguish the anomalies from your good examples.
从正常样本中区别出异常来
And so that's the
这就是误差分析的过程
process of error analysis
and using that to create
以及如何为异常检查算法
new features for anomaly detection.
建立新的特征变量
Finally, let me share with
最后 我想与你分享一些
you my thinking on how I
我平时在为异常检查算法
usually go about choosing features for anomaly detection.
选择特征变量时的一些思考
So, usually, the way I think about choosing features is
通常来说 我想到的选择特征变量的方法是
I want to choose features that will
我会选那些取值
take on either very, very
既不会特别特别大
large values, or very, very
也不会特别特别小的
small values, for examples
那些特征变量
that I think might turn out to be anomalies.
比如说
So let's use our example
我们还是用这个数据中心中
again of monitoring the computers in a data center.
监控计算机的例子
And so you have lots of
比如 在一个数据中心
machines, maybe thousands, or tens
你有很多台电脑
of thousands of machines in a data center.
也许上千 或者上万台
And we want to know if one
我们想要知道的是
of the machines, one of our
是不是有哪一台机器
computers is acting up, so doing something strange.
运作不正常了
So here are examples of features you may choose,
这里给出了几种可选的特征变量
maybe memory used, number of disc accesses, CPU load, network traffic.
包括占用内存 磁盘每秒访问次数 CPU负载 网络流量
But now, lets say that I
现在假如说
suspect one of the failure
我怀疑某个出错的情况
cases, let's say that
假如说 我认为
in my data set I think
在我的数据中
that CPU load the network traffic
我的CPU负载和网络流量
tend to grow linearly with each other.
应该互为线性关系
Maybe I'm running a bunch of
可能我运行了一组
web servers, and so, here
网络服务器
if one of my servers is
如果其中一个服务器
serving a lot of users,
在对许多用户服务
I have a very high CPU load, and have a very high network traffic.
那么我的CPU负载和网络流量都很大
But let's say, I think,
现在假如说
let's say I have a suspicion, that
我怀疑其中一个出错的情形
one of the failure cases is
是我的计算机在执行一个任务时
if one of my computers
进入了一个死循环
has a job that gets stuck in some infinite loop.
因此被卡住了
So if I think one of
意思就是说
the failure cases, is one of
假如我感觉
my machines, one of my
我的其中一台机器
web servers--server code--
或者说其中一台服务器的代码
gets stuck in some infinite loop,
执行到一个死循环卡住了
and so the CPU load grows,
因此CPU负载升高
but the network traffic doesn't because
但网络流量没有升高
it's just spinning it's
因为只是CPU执行了
wheels and doing a lot of CPU work, you know,
较多的工作 所以负载较大
stuck in some infinite loop.
卡在了死循环里
In that case, to detect
在这种情况下
that type of anomaly, I might
要检测出异常
create a new feature, X5,
我可以新建一个特征 x5
which might be CPU load
x5 等于 CPU负载
divided by network traffic.
除以网络流量
And so here X5 will take
因此 x5 的值
on a unusually large value
将会变得不寻常地大
if one of the machines has a
如果某一台机器
very large CPU load but
具有较大的CPU负载
not that much network traffic and
但网络流量正常的话
so this will be a
因此 这将成为一个
feature that will help your
很好的特征 能帮助你
anomaly detection capture, a certain type of anomaly.
检测出某种类型的异常情况
And you can
当然 你还可以
also get creative and come up with other features as well.
用同样的方法得到更多其他的特征
Like maybe I have a feature
比如说我可以
x6 thats CPU load
建立一个特征 x6
squared divided by network traffic.
等于 CPU负载的平方除以网络流量
And this would be another variant
这就像是特征 x5 的一个变体
of a feature like x5 to try
实际上它捕捉的异常
to capture anomalies where one
仍然是你的机器
of your machines has a very
是否具有一个比较高的
high CPU load, that maybe
CPU 负载 但没有一个
doesn't have a commensurately large network traffic.
同样很大的网络流量
And by creating features like
通过这样的方法
these, you can start to capture
建立新的特征变量
anomalies that correspond to
你就可以通过不同特征变量的组合
unusual combinations of values of the features.
捕捉到对应的不寻常现象
So in this video we
在这段视频中
talked about how to and
我们介绍了如何选择特征
take a feature, and maybe transform
以及对特征进行一些
it a little bit, so that
小小的转换
it becomes a bit more Gaussian,
让数据更像正态分布
before feeding into an anomaly detection algorithm.
然后再把数据输入异常检测算法
And also the error analysis
同时也介绍了建立特征时
in this process of creating features
进行的误差分析方法
to try to capture different types of anomalies.
来捕捉各种异常的可能
And with these sorts of guidelines hopefully that will help you
希望你通过这些方法
to choose good features, to give to
能够了解如何选择好的特征变量
your anomaly detection algorithm, to
从而帮助你的异常检测算法
help it capture all sorts of anomalies.
捕捉到各种不同的异常情况 【教育无边界字幕组】翻译：所罗门捷列夫 校对：竹二个 审核：小白_远游